Register to the The Vivian Perlis Collection of Schmitz, Ornstein, Copland, and Kirkpatrick
Yale University Music Library
The Vivian Perlis Collection of Schmitz, Ornstein, Copland, and Kirkpatrick
1914-2002
MSS 96
Yale University Music Library
0.5
(1 box)
Correspondence, an unpublished book, clippings, and other materials pertaining to E. Robert Schmitz and the Pro Musica Society, Leo Ornstein, Aaron Copland, and John Kirkpatrick
Perlis, Vivian
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Vivian Perlis Collection of Schmitz, Ornstein, Copland, and Kirkpatrick was acquired from Vivian Perlis in several installments between 1996 and 2004.
Associated Materials
Researchers may also be interested in MSS 54, The E. Robert Schmitz Papers; MSS 10, The Leo Ornstein Papers; and MSS 56, The John Kirkpatrick Papers (all in the Irving S. Gilmore Music Library of Yale University); as well as the Aaron Copland Collection (at the Library of Congress).
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open to researchers by appointment. There are no restricted materials in the collection. Please contact the Special Collections staff to schedule an appointment.
Biographical / Historical
E. Robert Schmitz (1889-1949) was an influential pianist, teacher, author, and organizer. Born in Paris, he settled in the United States after World War I, and founded Pro Musica, an international organization that promoted new music with concerts, lectures, and publications.
Leo Ornstein was born in Kremenchug, Russia (probably in 1893, although the date is not certain), and moved to New York in 1906. As a young man he quickly established a reputation as a piano virtuoso in the United States and Europe, and his bold compositions were as hotly debated as those of Schoenberg and Stravinsky. After more than a decade of celebrity, Ornstein withdrew from the public eye, and spent the remainder of his long life quietly teaching and composing. He died in Wisconsin in 2002.
Aaron Copland (1900-1990) ranks among the most widely respected of all American composers. Born in Brooklyn to a Russian Jewish family, Copland studied with Rubin Goldmark in New York and Nadia Boulanger in France. His music, which drew upon sources as disparate as jazz, neoclassicism, folk music, and serialism, helped establish an American musical vocabulary, and his most popular works, such as Appalachian Spring and Fanfare for the Common Man, have reached audiences far beyond the concert hall.
John Kirkpatrick (1905-1991) was a notable American pianist, scholar, and teacher, who was best known for performing, cataloguing, and editing the music of Charles Ives.
Vivian Perlis is a prominent historian of American music, and the founding director of the Oral History, American Music project at Yale University. In the course of her research, she worked closely with Leo Ornstein, Aaron Copland, and other notable musicians, and obtained many important documents, which were later acquired by the Gilmore Music Library.
Scope and Contents
Includes Fred Burrous's unpublished book about the Pro Musica Society and E. Robert Schmitz (which contains numerous letters and photographs); correspondence by and about Leo Ornstein and his wife (chiefly from the the Ornstein revival of the 1970s and '80s); clippings, programs, and other materials pertaining to Ornstein; and correspondence between Aaron Copland and John Kirkpatrick.
Arrangement
In 3 series as follows: I. E. Robert Schmitz and the Pro Musica society. II. Leo Ornstein. III. Aaron Copland and John Kirkpatrick.
Burrous, Fred, 1920- ( Story of Pro Musica); Copland, Aaron, 1900-1990; Kirkpatrick, John, 1905-1991; Ornstein, Leo, 1892-2002; Schmitz, E. Robert (Elie Robert), 1889-1949; Pro Musica (Society)
- E. Robert Schmitz and the Pro Musica society, 1913-1949; Series I
  - The Story of Pro Musica / by Fred Burrous., 1913-1945; Burrous, Fred; Ca. 116 p. (64 numbered p. of typescript interspersed with [23] unnumbered pages of photographs pasted in + 29 p. of "Pro Musica Documents?) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes letters (variously originals, photoreproductions, transcriptions, and translations) by Schoenberg, Prokofiev, Milhaud, Ravel, Mayer, de Falla, Belaiev, Casella, Toch, Tansman, and d'Indy.
    Includes numerous photographs (some autographed), but a few photographs appear to have been removed.
    The typescript itself is not dated, but various documents and photographs within it have dates ranging from 1913 to 1945.
  - The Story of Pro Musica: additional materials., 1919-1949 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Additional clippings, photographs, programs, correspondence, contracts, and other materials pertaining to Fred Burrous' unpublished book The Story of Pro Musica.
- Leo Ornstein, 1914-2002; Series II
  - Correspondence (Ornstein-Perlis), 1972-1986; 21 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Consists chiefly of letters from Pauline Ornstein or Leo Ornstein to Vivian Perlis. Also includes one letter to Ms. Hubbell with a postscript to Perlis, one letter to Claire Reis, and four items whose recipient is not identified. Three letters are incomplete.
  - Correspondence (other), 1917-2002; 53 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Consists chiefly of correspondence pertaining to the Ornstein revivial, beginning in the 1970s. Also includes one letter from the Musical Courier to Ornstein in 1917.
  - Newspaper articles, 1914-2002 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    General
    Also includes typescripts of some articles.
  - Newspaper articles, 1981-2001 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Articles, 1976-1982 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Pertaining to Yale-related events.
  - Journal and magazine articles, 1914-1976 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Journal and magazine articles, 1914-2002 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Programs and announcements, 1916-2002 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous, 1975-1998 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Includes honorary degree and citation from St. Norbert College (1987), a fragment of music from Ornstein's "A Morning in the Woods" (photocopy, p. 1 only), and promotional material from publishers and record companies.
- Aaron Copland and John Kirkpatrick, 1928-1960; Series III
  - Item lists, 2; lists (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Detailed inventories of the contents of the next two folders, prepared by library staff (?) and by John Kirkpatrick.
  - Correspondence, 1928-1945; 45 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Arrangement
    Arranged by type (letters, note, postcards, telegrams).
    Chiefly from Copland to Kirkpatrick.
  - Correspondence, 1940-1960; 14 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Includes correspondence from Kirkpatrick to Copland, and Kirkpatrick's correspondence pertaining to Copland with Victor Kraft, H.W. Heinsheimer, the League of Composers, and Julia Smith. Also includes a page of Kirkpatrick's corrections to an unidentified piano piece.